Alright
here we go. So today's דף daf is כ"ט, chaf tes, 29,
and we start with the משנה mishna at the bottom. We're in
the middle of a really fascinating set of משניות mishnayot which we
would not have expected in בכורות bechorot but are very important in
terms of a whole range of issues. Yesterday we dealt with the
question about
liability for a legal malpractice and whether it's because of גרמי garmi
or one only did it or one actually did it physically, but
then also the interesting question about what constitutes a wrong judgment as
opposed to no judgment at all. So bizarrely if you made something
that wasn't even considered a judgment at all, as long as you
didn't physically go ahead and take the money out of the person's
hands, you're somehow free of liability. And at the other end of
the spectrum, somebody with a license to judge, a מומחה לדין, mumcheh
l'din, is also free of liability. And we also mentioned the important
distinction between טועה בדבר משנה to'eh b'dvar mishna and טועה בשיקול הדעת,
to'eh b'shikul hadaas, that an error in judgment which is exactly this
question about what is considered a bad דין din as opposed to
not a דין din at all, that an error in judgment could
be a bad דין, din, whereas not a דין din at all
could
be a case of טועה בדבר משנה, to'eh b'dvar mishna, like making
a mistake in black letter law. And that leads to the major
that is the locus of the major discussion in the ראשונים rishonim
of essentially which texts are canonized, you know, which opinions, if somebody
makes a mistake in something that's in the גמרא, gemara, if somebody
makes a mistake in something that's in the גאונים, geonim, what exactly
is considered sort of binding and canonical law comes up in discussing
the parameters of טועה בדבר משנה. to'eh b'dvar mishna. Now we move
on from that to another to the issue about being paid for
your services when you are doing a religious type of a function.
So let's take a look at the משנה mishna at the bottom
of כ"ח עמוד ב', chaf chet amud bet, last משנה. mishna.
Yes, I was thinking also of the issue and I'm trying
to wrap it more clearly in
my head about is קיבלו עליהו kiblu aleihu or not. Yeah, קיבלו
עליהו kiblu aleihu would work against would
free you from liability, but
the גמרא gemara in סנהדרין sanhedrin discusses a scenario that it's קיבלו
עליהו kiblu aleihu under the conditions that you issued דין תורה. din
torah. Meaning if it's קיבלו עליהו kiblu aleihu as a type of
whatever you say we'll follow, then of course you would not have
liabilities, there would not be considered to be a טועה. to'eh. But
if it's קיבלו עליהו kiblu aleihu because normally you're not supposed to
go with a דיין אחד dayan echad or the person might be
a relative or whatever it was and it was but nevertheless the
stipulation was that it had to be a דין תורה din torah
that the person
gave, then it would still have all of this sense of error
and liability.
It's not mentioned here.
No, no, it's
in סנהדרין. sanhedrin. This is not discussed here. I should say the
other ambiguity here and with this we will move on is that
the case by the בכור, bechor, the reason that the person's you
know we buried the בכור bechor and we didn't trust his judgment
or whatever, I mean there's a question there about you know whether
he was דוקין שבעין, dukin she-ba-ayin, but anyway the case was that
the person was an אינו מומחה. eino mumcheh. He was you know
not licensed essentially, acknowledged to not be an expert. It does not
tell us what exactly the scenario is by the person that's דן
את הדין. dan es hadin. The next משנה mishna just goes in
and says, oh, and somebody makes a judgment, then you have to
pay up. It didn't say you made a wrong judgment. So by
juxtaposition the context seems to say that even if the judgment is
correct, if you are not licensed and authorized to be a דיין.
dayan. That is really what the משנה mishna sounds like by juxtaposition.
But the גמרא gemara in סנהדרין sanhedrin and even the גמרא gemara
here discuss the question about what type of mistake did you make?
Were you טועה בדבר משנה, to'eh b'dvar mishna, were you not טועה
בדבר משנה, to'eh b'dvar mishna, or טועה בשיקול הדעת? to'eh b'shikul hadaas?
And the case in the end with רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon was
a clear example where רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon made a mistake. So
there's a little ambiguity whether the case of דיינות dayanus here where
you pay and your liability is it because it's shown that you
actually made a mistake or is it like the בכור bechor case
where we don't care if you made a mistake or not, you
weren't licensed and therefore we'll treat it as if it were a
mistake. So that's a little bit ambiguous although the emphasis of the
גמרא gemara it's ambiguous in the משנה mishna well no but yeah
anyway the משנה mishna also has the רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon case.
Anyway the גמרא gemara seems to emphasize more the point that it
was that there was evidence that you actually made a mistake. Now
we turn on to the next משנה mishna which is the issue
about being paid for your services. Let's take a look. הנוטל שכר
לראות את הבכורות, hanotel sachar lirot es habechorot, somebody who takes a
fee for inspecting בכורות, bechorot, אין שוחטין על פיו, ein shochtin al
piv,
you cannot שחט shecht on his say-so, meaning even if he's an
expert and he knows what he's doing, the very fact that he's
being paid for it makes his rulings suspect.
unless he was an expert. Well, we already know you need a
מומחה *mumche*, but we're not done. Continuing to the top of the
עמוד א *amud aleph*. כאילו ביבנה *ke'ilo be'yavne* like Ilo who was
an expert bechor inspector in Yavne, התירו לו *heteeru lo* they allowed
him חכמים *chachamim* להיות נוטל ארבע איסרות לבהמה דקה *lihyos notel arba
issaros l'behema daka* to take four איסרות *issarot*, which is a small
relatively small coin, whatever it is, let's say four dollars for a
בהמה דקה *behema daka* ושישה לגסה *v'shisha l'gassa* and six for a
לגסה *l'gassa*, a large animal, a cow, בין תם tam בין בעל
מום baal mum. *bein tam bein ba'al mum* whether he would rule
that it would have a blemish or wouldn't have a blemish, he
would get a flat fee. Now, why is he different is not
exactly clear. We'll see in a minute. But the other point is
I think worth emphasizing is the idea that it's a flat fee.
You can understand the importance of taking a flat fee, because if
you get paid only for a beneficial ruling, which is the בעל
מום baal mum. *ba'al mum*, then obviously there's an incentive, even subconscious,
you know, to find it as a בעל מום baal mum *ba'al
mum*. Even although the owner, of course, why should he pay you
if you didn't give him a helpful ruling, but nevertheless, you certainly
understand the importance in terms of the institution that it be a
flat fee. Now, why was Ilo an exception? The Gemara is not
going to say. Let's just look at the first line here of
Rashi. כאילו הדר ביבנה דחסיד הוה ולא נחשד בכך *ke'ilo hadar be'yavne
dechasid hava v'lo nechshad bekach*. He was so pious that either that
we had no objective suspicion and maybe nobody else would have suspected
that this would have at all influenced his rulings. Okay? So it
was a flat fee and b, that he was so pious that
there was no concern that his rulings might have been influenced. Let's
read the Gemara and then we're going to reflect back on that.
So let's see what the Gemara says. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama, *mai
ta'ama*, what's the reason that you pay more for a cow than
for a sheep? האי נפיש טירחיה והאי לא נפיש טירחיה *hai nafish
tirchei v'hai lo nafish tirchei*, one is a lot of effort, one
is not a lot of effort. Why is it more effort? Well,
you might think that a cow is like larger, so there's more
to inspect, but not really, because the person is pointing out to
you a specific thing that he thinks is a מום *mum*. You're
not doing the whole inspection of the whole animal. The owner says,
'Hey, I think I've got a מום *mum* here,' and you look
at it. So why is it more effort by a cow? So
if you look at Rashi, Rashi says, גסה נפיש טירחייהו להשליכה לארץ
לכפותה וליראות מומה *gassa nafish tirchaihu l'hashlicha l'aretz l'chpota v'liros muma*. You
have to throw it on the ground, I mean, you know, get
it to lie down, and that's a lot harder for a cow,
you know, I mean, just think you know you know this whole
thing about how they do שחיטה *shechita* of cows and they have
all these like major devices, some people, you know, stunning is a
whole issue. Do stunning for שחיטה *shechita* but then they have these
like tumblers. It's very hard to get a cow to lie down.
So therefore, that additional effort is what you would pay him more
for. Of course, one wonders why the inspector had to do that,
why you couldn't get some other people to do that. But nevertheless,
that's the additional effort. Did you want to say something, Michael?
No? Okay, fine. So now let's take a look. בין תם tam
בין בעל מום baal mum. *bein tam bein ba'al mum*, regardless of
whether it was found to have a blemish or not. So the
Gemara says like this. בשלמא בעל מום baal mum משום דקא שרי
shari, ליה *bishlama ba'al mum mishum deka shari lei*, I understand why
the owner's going to pay you for it's a בעל מום baal
mum *ba'al mum*. You did him something that was beneficial to him.
You made the animal permitted. אלא תם tam מאי *ela tam mai*,
but what's the reason that you pay him for a non-blemished animal?
I mean, you know, why should you spend the money? He didn't
do you any favor. No, דאם כן אתי למיחשדיה *de'im ken ati
l'michshdei*, because if you only pay him when he gives you the
beneficial result, then people will come to suspect him. And maybe even
Ilo, who is such a pious person, you know, maybe even if
it won't really influence him, and maybe it will, and anyway, maybe
people will have that suspicion. דאמרי האי בעל מום תם tam, הוא
והאי דקא שרי ליה משום אגרא *d'amri hai ba'al mum tam hu
v'hai deka shari lei mishum agra*, and people will say, this thing
that he's saying is a בעל מום *ba'al mum*, it's really a
תם tam, *tam*, and why did he permit it? Because he was
getting paid to favor it was a בעל מום *ba'al mum*. So
the Gemara says, אי הכי *ei hachi*, if that's true, תם נמי
*tam nami* even now that you have this system that he gets
paid regardless, so that even if he's a
תם *tam* people will suspect him. Why will they suspect him? So
אמרי בעל מום הוא והאי דלא קא שרי ליה סבר כי היכי
דלישקול אגרא זימנא אחריתי *amri ba'al mum hu v'hai d'lo ka shari
lei savar ki heichi d'lishkol agra zimna achriti*, because they'll say, you
know what, it's really בעל מום *ba'al mum* and why didn't he
say it was a בעל מום *ba'al mum*? He thinks that as
long as I rule it's a תם *tam* you'll keep on bringing
it back and I'll get paid again and again until I finally
decide that it's a בעל מום *ba'al mum*. So even if it's
a flat fee, they'll suspect that the reason he ruled that it
was a תם *tam* was in order to get increased business from
this one guy.
Although, of course, it might make him lose out business from other
people if they see how hard it is to get a ruling.
But anyway, so the Gemara says there's reason to suspect in that
case as well. So the Gemara says, חדא זימנא תקינו ליה רבנן
תרתי זימני לא תקינו ליה רבנן *chada zimna takinu lei rabanan tarti
zimnei lo takinu lei rabanan*. No. Apparently, this idea that the rabbis
allowed Ilo to get this paid this fee, so the rabbis set
up the structure. They allowed it and they decided how much you
get paid. You get paid the same for a תם *tam* and
for a בעל מום *ba'al mum*. So those same rabbis said that,
no, if it's for the same animal, you only get paid once.
And therefore, even if you rule it's a תם *tam* and he
brings it back again, you're not going to get paid a second
time. So therefore we're not afraid that he said it was a
תם to get repeat business. Of course there's an obvious problem here.
What's the obvious problem? If you only get paid once for the
same animal, why? Once
per
inspector per animal?
What?
Once per inspector per animal, yeah.
But what's the problem?
A person gets a reputation for being lenient, people will come to
him
more
and more frequently.
Well that's true, but we're not making a general institution here. I
mean yes of course you would always go to the person who
gives you the more lenient rulings. But we're not making a general
principle, we're saying for אילא. Ila. What? Generally speaking, a person would
rather not be bothered with people coming back to him. But if
he gets paid and
he gets a reputation as someone who will be lenient, people will
come to him more often as a matter
of
course.
Okay, so I mean so you're just saying in general to even
allow this in the case of אילא, Ila, there's the concern that
it's just you know, but again if we're assuming that אילא Ila
is being honest and people are coming to him, so what's lost?
He's getting paid for his time, he's giving good rulings. No, the
problem is that if imagine this, I'm אילא, Ila, I'm getting paid
the same whether I rule it's a תם or בעל מום. But
I'm also told that if I rule that it's a תם and
I get my four זוז zuz or whatever I'm getting, then I'm
not going to get paid the next few times the owner brings
me the animal to inspect because I've already gotten paid once. So
therefore what? I've got an incentive to say that it's a בעל
מום. I've got an incentive to say that it's a בעל מום
so I don't have to look at this animal ten times and
I'm only going to get paid once for the animal. Right, you
understand the
problem? Yes.
I thought this was the second תקנה takana as opposed to...
No, the first תקנה, takana, no the second, the תקנה takana was
that I do not get paid more, if I get paid more
than once for the same animal, I'll rule that it's a תם
and then you'll keep on bringing it and I'll keep on getting
paid. If I only get paid once for the animal, then why
then I have an incentive to rule it's a בעל מום. Because
if I rule it's a תם, then you're going to bring it
again and again and again and I'm not going to get paid
again. So why go through the effort? Why not rule it's a
בעל מום now and be done with it? Right?
He can always refuse to look at it again.
Ah, so that's what תוספות Tosafot says. If you look at תוספות,
Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says תרי זימני לא תקינו ליה רבנן. trei zimnei
lo takinu lei rabanan. תוספות Tosafot says ואם תאמר אכהתי אמרו האי
טעמא הוא דהאי דשרי ליה לפי שאינו רוצה לטרוח פעם אחרת. v'im
tomar akahati amru hai ta'am hu d'hai d'shari lei lefi she'eino rotze
litrach pa'am acheret.
Maybe people will just say oh yeah, he said it's a בעל
מום but he's just but it's really a תם, he just doesn't
want to have to look at it again. So the גמרא Gemara
says ויש לומר שלא חיובו חכמים לראות פעם אחרת. v'yesh lomar shelo
chiyu hu chachamim lirot pa'am acheret. You don't have an obligation to
look at it again. אלא דאם ראוהו הוא דאין יכול ליטול עליו
שכר. ela d'im ra'ahu hu d'ein yachol litol alav sachar. If I
look at it again I can't ask for another payment, but I
can always refuse it again. So therefore nobody's going to suspect me
that I'm doing it to make my life easier because I always
have the right of refusal the next time that it's brought. Okay,
so I mean so that's and then he has another answer that
you know, we wouldn't suspect you that far. Anyway, so that's what
we have but that's only allowed by אילא. Ila. The general point
is that you can't get paid because it puts your you know,
even with אילא Ila that we allowed it, we structured it in
a certain way to remove suspicion, but with a normal person even
that we wouldn't allow presumably because you know, anytime you're getting paid,
anytime money is involved, there's always some question about objectivity. Even with
the system of that getting paid equally regardless of ruling, presumably אילא
Ila was the one exception. Now רש״י Rashi said he was the
exception because he was very pious. Let's take a look, continue looking
at the גמרא Gemara and then we're going to go back and
think about the case of אילא. Ila. So let's look now at
the next case.
Because now it goes beyond בכור bechor just like the other discussion
about liability went beyond בכור. bechor. הנוטל שכרו לדון, ha'notel sacharo ladun,
if somebody gets a fee for giving rulings on a בית דין,
beit din, somebody's a דיין dayan on a בית דין, beit din,
a judge. דיניו בטילים, dinav betelin, his judgments are nullified.
להעיד, leha'id, to testify, עדותו בטילה, eduto betela, his testimony is thrown
out.
So much for the whole field, you know there's a major field
in America right about being an expert witness at trials, and it
pays very well.
And that raises very serious questions about objectivity. If you're being paid
and you're being paid well, so you know, how objective are you
really being? So here we
what? I've been asked to do that many times. Oh you've been
asked to do that
many times? Yeah. And what happens if you tell the side that
you won't be able to testify the way they want? And they
say thank you for your services goodbye, right? And you still get
paid
and you don't ever get asked to do it again.
There you go.
I know.
So there you go. So you can understand what this is about.
Now the obvious question is isn't this just not a case of
שוחד? shochad? So let's continue with the גמרא. Gemara. with what at
least is by a judge. So let's read this משנה. mishnah.
So if you can say that both parties put up this amount
and then they say the winner gets it or whatever.
Could be and that would take it out of שוחד shochad but
it wouldn't take it out of the case of our משנה. mishnah.
So let's take a look, let's read our משנה mishnah and then
we'll discuss it. So if you get a fee for judging it's
your judgment's thrown out, if you get a fee for testifying your
testimony is thrown out, is nullified. להזות ולקדש lehazot ulekadesh
now how about something that's not about about sort of judgment or
subjectivity or you know about a decision or honesty? Let's say you're
getting fee paid just for some מצוה mitzvah act. To sprinkle the
ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah or to sanctify the ashes of
פרה אדומה parah adumah by mixing it with the waters of a
well. So then מימיו מי מערה meimav mei me'arah the water you
use is like the water of a cave meaning it's not considered
like well water, it's not
מים חיים. mayim chayim. אפרו אפר מקלה afro efer mikleh your ashes
are like just ashes from a fireplace. There it completely loses its
status as ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah because you got paid.
So now it's not just about honesty and integrity, it's just the
fact that you're never supposed to get paid when you're doing a
מצוה. mitzvah. You're not supposed to mix up מצוה mitzvah and making
money. מצוה mitzvah should just be for doing the מצוה. mitzvah. אם
היה כהן im hayah kohen now.
Wait, להזות ולקדש, lehazot ulekadesh, are these the only מצוות? mitzvot? Why
does it mention these? Why why these two?
Okay, so it is true that this משנה mishnah only says these.
I don't know, I suppose that's true that you could imagine that
there's a power involved with פרה אדומה parah adumah in the sense
that you know you're determining somebody's purity. So even though this person
is just doing the preparation, somehow you involve money in it, you
know money and power you know can can be given to abuse.
I hadn't thought about that but that's possible to read the משנה
mishnah this way.
Even though the actual act there's nothing that the person could do
wrong, we don't want money to be involved in the process. But
I will say that maybe the reason I was inclined to read
it more more abstractly is because the גמרא gemara does. So the
גמרא gemara for example as we're going to see in a minute
turns it to the issue about תלמוד תורה, talmud torah, although there
too you could say there's a power differential. But the גמרא gemara
also turns it to issues about like השבת אבידה hashavat aveidah and
like a lot of other מצוות mitzvot that the גמרא gemara applies
this principle that you're never supposed to be paid for the doing
of a מצוה. mitzvah. So the גמרא gemara in other places abstracts
this. But you are certainly correct that in this משנה mishnah it
would be possible to limit it to specifically these two cases. So
let's...
But why would the גמרא gemara abstract it? Why would they single
out פרה אדומה parah adumah though? Isn't it supposed to be any
of the other תרי"ג?
taryag? Yeah, it's it's a very good point. You know, I
I suppose I intuitively thought that it's going to like the opposite
extreme. That it is something that is you know completely not about
subjectivity and it's just
and it's just about like preparing this material and nevertheless we're so
much against being paid for it that you know we're going to
have this very severe consequence. It's also a case where we can
negate the results of your actions. Like you know in other types
of מצוות, mitzvot, you know for example if like there's cases like
you know I see your field is about to get flooded and
I drop my you know and I drop my thing in order
to go and run and save your field, can I get paid,
not, etc. We can't so there's a question of do I can
I get paid for having done a מצוה? mitzvah? But we can't
negate my actions. You can throw out a judgment, throw out testimony,
throw out the ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So that's
what I had always sort of I guess implicitly assumed. That number
one it's similar in that you can throw out the result and
number two it also provides a very serious contrast that it's a
case that has absolutely no judgment involved and there's no concern about
honesty and nevertheless this is how far we go. So that's how
I read it and that you know but that's through the lens
of the גמרא gemara that assumes that this is a general principle
about never being paid for any מצוה. mitzvah. I can see the
alternative read where it's דוקא davka things that maybe have to do
with not only honesty but also with power. It's an interesting it's
an interesting thought about this משנה.
mishnah. Yeah, because you can't sprinkle the ashes on yourself, you're completely
dependent on somebody.
Yeah, I understand, I get it.
And potentially potentially save your own field so there's no way you
can keep yourself from being אדם המעוניין adam hame'unyan unless someone else
is involved.
No, I understand it, I understand that it's possible to read it
to be to be you know to be emphasizing this as as
particularly problematic. It's a good point, it's a very good point.
Also the פרה אדומה parah adumah was really expensive and you know
maybe people would think there's an incentive to like you know play
the system to somehow not lose out by ten million dollars or
however much it was, you know given all the stories we had.
Maybe we were saying we're going so far even in that kind
of a case, even a פרה אדומה parah adumah which is an
extremely rare and valuable commodity.
Right, right. That's how I had initially assumed that that was the
point. That it was something very valuable, it was something that was
no concern about honesty and objectivity and nevertheless this was a consequence.
But it could also be as is being suggested that it's דוקא
*davka* this because this is something that has a real issue about
a power differential. So I think that those are both excellent reads.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does generalize it. Let's keep on reading the
משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*. אם היה כהן Kohen *im hayah kohein*, now let's
say it was a כהן Kohen *kohein* who had to come and
testify and judge, and as a result of having to get to
the בית דין Beis Din *beis din* he became טמא tamei, *tamei*
in the way he was traveling, ומטמאו מטומאתו
*metame'o mitumato* and now that he is טמא tamei, *tamei* he can
no longer eat his תרומה terumah. *terumah* because he has to buy
חולין *chulin* food which is more expensive. So now we're talking about
we're not going to pay you for your services but can we
pay you for your expenses? As a result of having to come
and testify I had to become טמא tamei? *tamei* and now I
had to buy more expensive food. Can you at least pay me
for my expenses? So then מאכילו ומשקו *ma'achilo umashko* you can feed
him you can put sort of what's it called with oil or
you can have him drink excuse me and you can pay him
for his expenses. Now it's interesting it seems like you could only
pay him for the difference I mean even if I was sitting
at home I have to buy lunch and dinner. So you pay
him for the additional cost not just you give him straight a
food allowance but it's the additional cost that was a result of
having to come and testify because I got טמא tamei. *tamei* and
I couldn't use my own food. וסכו *vesacho* and then you also
anoint him not anoint him whatever it's called oil that they would
do for
lubricant for keeping their skin moist. So again that is something that
he could have used תרומה *terumah* for and now he cannot. ואם
היה זקן *ve'im hayah zakein* now let's see he was elderly and
he could not go on his own and he had to hire
a car service then מרכיבו על al. החמור *markivo al hachamor* so
you pay for the car service you pay for the donkey ונותן
לו שכרו scharo. כפועל *venosein lo secharo kepo'el* and one final thing
you do is you give him his fee as a worker. Now
that is interesting the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will basically mean that that
is you pay him for his time not for his services and
exactly how you draw the line between time and services we will
talk in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. But the basic point is you
cannot be paid for the actual service that you're doing what you
can be paid is for related expenses and the fact that you
are taking off time from other things and giving us of your
time. So if anybody's ever been on jury duty how much do
they pay you per day on jury duty? What is it? Some
stupid
amount. What?
How much? Thirty
dollars a day.
Thirty dollars a day.
I think in civil court I think it's twenty dollars a day.
Oh so it's less than minimum wage. Okay. So anyway so that
is basically that is something symbolic about paying for your time although
extremely trivial. We will see what that is in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. Let's read the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* now. מנא הני מילי *minani
hani mili* where does this come from? That you're not supposed to
do it with a fee that you're not supposed to do it
with a fee. So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב דאמר קרא *amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav de'amar kra* because the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* says
ראה למדתי אתכם חקים ומשפטים כאשר צוני ה' אלהי *re'eh limadeti etchem
chukim umishpatim ka'asher tzivani Hashem Elokai*. Behold I have taught you judgments
and laws as ה' *Hashem* my as ה' *Hashem* my God has
taught me. So I taught you like God has taught me or
God has commanded me actually. מה אני בחנם אף אתם בחנם *ma
ani bechinam af atem bechinam*. The same way I am teaching you
for free and I also did not ask you for any payment
when I taught you you also should not teach must teach others
for free. And also might be suggesting also the same way God
taught me for free I am teaching you for free and therefore
you should teach others for free.
תניא נמי הכי *tanya nami hachi* we taught similarly. One minute. כאשר
צוני ה' אלהי
*ka'asher tzivani Hashem Elokai* as ה' *Hashem* my God has commanded me.
מה אני בחנם אף
אתם בחנם *ma ani bechinam af atem bechinam*. So
the same way
I
teach for
free you
teach for free.
ומנין שאם לא מצא בחנם שילמד בשכר *uminayin she'im lo matza bechinam
sheyilmad bischar*?
How do I know that if you cannot find somebody to teach
you for free that you should be prepared to pay for your
learning? תלמוד לומר Talmud Lomar אמת קנה *talmud lomar emet kneh*. Purchase
truth. So if you can't find it for free don't go only
to the person who does it for free even though he's much
worse. If you have to spend money and you have to pay
somebody and somebody is demanding a fee even though he shouldn't. then
pay the money. אמת קנה. ומניין שלא יאמר כשם שלמדתיה בשכר כך
אלמדנה בשכר. Uminayin shelo yomar kshem shelimadetiya besachar kach alamdenah besachar.
Now let's say you learned because you shelled out a lot of
money because somebody wouldn't teach without a fee. Should you say well,
heck, if that's what he did to me I'm going to do
that to the now that I'm a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham I'm
going to demand also a payment? No. תלמוד לומר the verse teaches
you אמת קנה ואל תמכור. emes kneh veal timkor.
Truth you should purchase but you should not sell it. So when
you come you should be prepared to spend a lot of money
but you have to maintain the right standards when it comes to
your own teaching and understand that it should be given freely.
Now let's unpack this. First of all, what's the point of pointing
out that you should be prepared to spend money? On the one
hand it could just be telling you מוסר mussar or telling you
that it should be taught for or whatever not מוסר mussar advice.
You know, we're telling you that it should be taught for free,
don't, you know, but nevertheless you should be prepared to spend money,
your education is more important than anything else even if the teachers
are not doing the right thing. But besides sort of telling you
מוסר mussar or good advice what it could also be doing is
contrasting it to the משנה. Mishna In the משנה Mishnah? if somebody
gets paid we basically throw the judgment out, throw out the ashes
of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Maybe we would have made a
similar a similar תקנה takkana here. Maybe we would have said if
somebody's demanding fee for his teaching then it's אסור assur to go
to him, right? You know, his תורה Torah is בטל. batel. But
it's interesting for the but but you know for the sort of
because of the of the supreme value of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
we don't say that.
We allow we allow we say we say go ahead and you
can even actually pay this guy if it's necessary. We're not going
to throw it out the same way we throw out other things.
So that's interesting in terms of expressing sort of how we're willing
to turn a blind eye to this even though we don't approve
of it for the value of תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. Now the
obvious question that the next questions that people are going to ask
is so great so how do you pay how do we pay
teachers?
And there the answer has a lot to do with you know
with basically the principle of שכר בטלה schar batala which we're going
to get to at the end of today's דף daf that you
pay somebody for their time that they're not pursuing another profession. Now
the problem with that is that would mean that would mean that
what what let me finish that would mean that you should in
principle not pay somebody for their seniority or how good of a
job they're doing in their current job but you should really pay
them for their you know for how much they could make in
another profession. So if a person left being a lawyer or doctor
to be a teacher they should get a much higher salary than
somebody who has no other marketable skills if all you're really doing
is paying them for for for the time they took off and
you're not really or for the fact that they're leaving something else
rather than for actually the service that they are providing. The answer
to that so there's a lot of תורה Torah on this meaning
there's a lot of הלכה halacha that discusses how we get from
the idea that you're not supposed to be paid for a מצוה
mitzvah to actually paying people to be teachers and רבנים rabbanim and
so on. One answer is if you look in תוספות. Tosafos. Let
me just find the right line in תוספות. Tosafos.
So the תוספות מה אני בחינם Tosafos mah ani bechinam in the
middle of תוספות Tosafos he says like this. He says ואין לתמוה
על דייני גזירות. Vein litmoah al dayanei gezeirot.
The line starts with the word על. It is three lines below
the כד kaf daled in brackets. So he says you should not
be astounded on דייני גזירות שבשכר היו נוטלין שכר מתרומת הלשכה. dayanei
gezeirot shebishchar hayu notlin schar mitrumat halishka. The גמרא Gemara says that
these people that were sort of fixed judges in ירושלים Yerushalayim got
paid from the temple treasury. How could they get paid? They were
sitting all day in judging. Don't we say you're not supposed to
pay judges? דבלאו טעמא דאגר בטלה דמוכח
שהיו Debelav taama deagar batala demuchach shehayu without saying they're getting paid
for taking time off from other work it's permitted. Why? דכיון דכל
עסקם היה על זה. Dekivan dechol askam haya al ze.
Since this was all they did with their time and it's not
they took out a you know an half hour to do something.
This was what they devoted their day to.
ולא היו עוסקים בשום מלאכה. Velo hayu oskim beshum melacha. They didn't
have any other job. על כרחם צריכים להתפרנס. Al korcham tzrichim lehitparnes.
So they had to be provided by communal funds which means it's
not שכר בטלה. schar batala. It's not like oh you're leaving another
job and even if you don't have any other marketable maybe you
don't have any other marketable skills but we are saying that when
it when you are doing something sort of when you are devoting
your time and you are and you need to make a פרנסה
parnassah everybody needs to make a פרנסה parnassah you know then sort
of has a that is something that we want to support and
we're going to make an exception to the rule that is something
that is worth paying for and we will make an exception of
not to not pay. Now of course problem with that is you
know it's still a little bit problematic because what makes it if
the issue were let's say being a judge and the concern were
about sort of about like you know honesty and integrity and so
on
and propriety then you could sort of say well obviously first of
all if he's being paid from communal funds there's not an honesty
issue and a propriety issue also doesn't really look so bad because
he's dedicating his entire time to it. But if you frame it
as the idea that you're not supposed to get paid for a
מצוה mitzvah even if you're not you know even if you're not
doing any anything else and it's of course important for the society
to have this institution about teachers that are devoting their whole time,
you know, it still is a little bit I think it's still
a little bit hard to exactly say what but still you're getting
paid for doing a מצוה, Mitzvah, you know, how does the fact
that you should how do those two things actually negate one another?
They might override, meaning the benefits of the community might override the
concern that you're not supposed to get paid for a מצוה. Mitzvah.
But it's not exactly like it like it neutralizes it, it might
just override it, meaning a larger sort of value, a larger concern,
which by the way, we already see in the case of תלמוד
תורה Talmud Torah that we don't say it's אסור Assur to go
somebody who for to somebody who's charging. We say the value of
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah overrides. So in the same way, we would
say having a dedicated teacher is an over is an overriding value.
So that's one question about paying our teachers and you could also
lead it into like paying full-time rabbis, although, you know, that also
gets into interesting questions. The רמב"ם Rambam has a whole tirade against
certainly about כולל Kollel people who are just sitting and learning, but
people that are doing services for the community, that's one thing and
devoting all their time to it. Now the other question is, how
do you get from תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah to our משנה? Mishnah
Right, this is only about תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, maybe it's exactly
about this idea that the pursuit of תורה Torah and of truth
should be pure, you know, what does it have to do with
other things which are more like, you know, services? So if you
look at רש"י Rashi and anyway, you know, maybe it's whatever, even
just גזירת הכתוב, Gezeras Hakasuv, maybe it's just talking about תורה. Torah.
So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, מנא הני
מילי דאינו שכר על ההוראה ותלמוד תורה שילמד. Mina hani mili de'eino
sechar al hahora'ah vetalmud torah sheyilamed.
So רש"י Rashi says on הוראה Hora'ah
on giving rulings and he might be connecting to the part of
the פסוק Pasuk? that says חוקים ומשפטים, Chukim Umishpatim, right? משה Moshe
is not just talking about תורה Torah in like he's talking about
the laws and following the laws and teaching what the laws are.
So the connection of giving a ruling in בית דין Beis Din
to the area to תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, obviously those are intertwined
concepts. So that might be where we're making that jump, but also
as I said to you before, this is a this is a
principle that the גמרא Gemara
abstracts to all מצוות. Mitzvos. So if it's abstracting to all מצוות,
Mitzvos, it's not just a question of connecting the dots from תלמוד
תורה Talmud Torah to פרה אדומה Parah Adumah or תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah to דין, Din, it's basically תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah to everything.
So fine, we look at it as a paradigm, it's not about
תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, it's about מצוות Mitzvos and then it's a
general principle you don't get paid for מצוות. Mitzvos. Now what that
still does not answer is why do you throw out the judgment?
Right, the same way if I have to pay I pay for
my תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah,
and right, so why here what's where do you learn that the
judgment is בטל? Batel? So basically everybody assumes that that idea that
the judgment is בטל Batel is rabbinic, is not biblical. The תורה
Torah doesn't tell you that it has a consequence of negating what
is when it's paid. That's a rabbinic תקנה Takkanah in order to
prevent this from happening and as I said, we did not and
we applied it to teaching, we applied it to ruling, we applied
it to פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, we did not go so far
to apply it to תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. Now, why don't you
say one minute, I have a better reason why the judgment is
בטל? Batel? It's שוחד, Shochad, right? So it's and you know, כי
השוחד יעור עיני Ki hashochad ye'aver einei and why do you need
this פסוק? pasuk. Why don't we learn it out from שוחד, Shochad,
from bribery? So תוספות Tosafos says no, bribery is being paid from
only one side and it's certainly with the hope that the judge
is going to try to work hard, you know, either directly ruling
in your benefit or putting in a little extra effort. Meaning the
רמ"א Rema says שוחד Shochad is forbidden even if the judge takes
the שוחד Shochad and says with the intent to with the intent
to to
be objective. Nevertheless, even if that's the judge's intent, the intent of
the person giving it is that the person is that the judge
is going to work a little bit harder on his behalf. So
here it is not שוחד Shochad because it might be that it's
paid by communal funds, it might be that it's paid equally by
both sides. It might be framed completely as payment for services and
not to find a particular, you know, end result. But with all
of that being said, even if it's not שוחד, Shochad, it still
is we're going to throw it out because we don't want money
involved at all in this process. We don't want involved in judgment,
we don't want involved in testimony. So as a rabbinic גזירה Gezerah
or as a rabbinic תקנה Takkanah we're going to throw it out,
we're going to throw out פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, we're not going
to throw out the תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, okay? And that is
again the difference. We allow that institution for we allow it for
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah in the same way we might allow the
whole institution of teachers. But I I should end by saying that
by when it comes to judgment,
there are some exceptions as well because there is the exception of
the דייני גזירות Dayanei Gezeros that תוספות Tosafos mentioned about the institution
of the sitting בית דין that got paid. So there are also
cases where we make exceptions even there and we don't always apply
this principle that we're throwing out the judgment. So that is basically
again I I went on a little bit at length, but that
is basically some of the key points. So let me just review
them and then I'll take any questions. Number one is, you're not
supposed to get paid at all for מצוות, Mitzvos, although the משנה
Mishna only mentions some, the גמרא Gemara abstracts. It starts with the
case of תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. So you're not supposed to get
paid. Number two is, some of the times we throw things out,
and that is assumed to be דרבנן. d'rabbanan. We throw out the
judgment. It's not just שוחד shochad because it would be communal, it
would be shared, it would not, it would be fee. Nevertheless, we
don't want money involved, so we throw it out. We throw out
the testimony, we throw out the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. There are
other times where we don't throw it out, like תלמוד תורה, Talmud
Torah, there the value of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is supreme and
we're not going to, you know, and maybe the concern about how
money might affect the result is maybe less. So therefore, by the
תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, we don't throw it out. In addition to
that, there are times where we allow for people to dedicate themselves
full-time to a certain position. What would that be? That would be
like full-time teachers, full-time rabbis, full-time דיינים, dayanim, and so on. And
there are times where we allow that, and that's not just framed
as שכר בטלה sechar battalah because then it would be maybe only
a very little amount of money, but that is framed as sort
of a societal need that trumps these other types of concerns. And
that is equivalent both when it comes to like teachers and דיינים.
dayanim. And now I should just say that the ראש Rosh goes
back to the case of אילא ביבנה Ila b'Yavneh and says that
the reason he was an exception was not because he was a
חסיד, chasid, but the reason he was an exception was because he
did it full-time. So he wants to read the case of אילא
ביבנה Ila b'Yavneh to be like the case that תוספות Tosafot mention
about the full-time judges in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, so are there any
questions before we continue?
I have a question. So when the משנה Mishna is saying שכר
בטלה, sechar battalah, it must be someone part-time, otherwise it would be
everything we said before, right? Because it says he has to be
בטל.
batel. Right. So the משנה Mishnah, is talking about a non-full-time judge
and about somebody that's just taking off from work to do it
as an ad hoc thing. Right.
And the other thing is, I mean, clearly it has to be
דרבנן, d'rabbanan, the not taking שכר מצוות, sechar mitzvot, because of the
פסוק. pasuk. I mean, it's probably one of these cases where they
had an idea and just wanted to read it into a פסוק.
It's not
the other way around.
That could very well be.
Anyway, all right. Any other questions?
All right.
Anyway, if you want to see the line in the ראש Rosh
who talks about teachers, I'll just read it to you. The ראש
Rosh says like
this: ומה שנהגו האידנא ללמוד בשכר, u'mah she'nahagu idna lilmod b'sechar, אם
אין לו במה להתפרנס, im ein lo b'mah l'hitparnes, שרי, if you
have no other פרנסה, parnassah, which is the exact opposite of שכר
בטלה, sechar battalah, okay? Because this is your full-time job and you
maybe have no other skills. Nevertheless, it's permissible.
He
says why: שמניח כל עסקיו ומשאו ומתנו, she'maniach kol asakav u'masa'o u'matano,
מסתבר דחשיב, mistavar d'chashiv, whatever, da da da.
Okay, anyway, that's basically what he says. So we allow it basically
because of the importance of that institution. Also, the גמרא Gemara says
that if you're teaching small kids, you get paid because half of
your job is to just be a babysitter. All right, but anyway,
moving up. Wait, I have another question.
So what
about
someone
who's independently wealthy or the day is at night or something? Right?
So that
is
not a factor, getting paid?
Yeah, that's a good point. I mean, you know, according to, it
might really be that if somebody is teaching in the day and
is independently wealthy or like makes some investments, spends an hour at
night and makes, you know, hundreds of thousands of dollars or whatever,
that that person על פי הלכה al pi halacha really should not
be taking money for his, for his teaching.
You know, there is interesting literature, you know, תשובות teshuvot on that,
but that type of a case at least prima facie is somebody
that maybe should not be being, should not be taking money, that's
true. Now, the question is, if he won't work without being paid
and he's a good teacher, then it's the flip side of it:
מנין אם לא מצא בחינם ילמדנו בשכר. minayin im lo matza b'chinam
yilamdenu b'sechar. The school shouldn't refuse to hire him, but in terms
of his, because you know, we do what it takes for תלמוד
תורה, Talmud Torah, but he should be, but he should be teaching
for free in that type of a scenario.
Why the כהנים Kohanim are supposed to be teachers of תורה Torah
and that's why they were supported by the whole community, right? Initially,
they were the
teachers.
Right. So you're saying that you do pay people. But again, you
know, that's sort of the question about this person who's fully dedicated
to it. If somebody is fully dedicated to it, so then it's
more like you are, you know, and maybe this also explains why
it's allowed. It's more like a, you know, it's more like a
living stipend than it is a fee. You are going to pay
this person not directly for their services, but you're going to pay
them to devote themselves to this and to leave and to not
be involved in other things.
So that's more the concept by the כהנים. Kohanim. You would not,
they would not teach you and you'd give them a ten dollar
fee for the class. You would support them as a whole and
the לויים, Levi'im, you would support them, their, you know, you would
pay for them to, you'd give them
food. food and sustenance so that they could devote themselves to these
types of service. So in a way that is similar to this
institute to what we're saying about somebody who is not who is
not doing any other pursuit and devoting themselves to do this, that
you want to support that. And so you're right, it's a good
analogy, it's a good to the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, so let's continue
in the גמרא, Gemara. let's get at least a little further. So
the גמרא Gemara says, להזות ולקדש מימיו מי מערה ואפרו מאפר מקלה,
Lehazot u'lekadesh mimav mei ma'arah ve'afro me'efer makleh, so if he's getting
paid for פרה אדומה Parah Adumah then it all gets thrown out.
ורמינהו, U'reminhu, I'll ask you on this, המקדש במי חטאת ובאפר חטאת
הרי זו מקודשת. Ha'mekadesh be'mei chatat u've'efer chatat harei zu mekudeshet. If
somebody gives the water of פרה אדומה Parah Adumah or the ashes
of פרה אדומה Parah Adumah to a woman for כסף קידושין, kesef
kiddushin, it works. אף על פי שהוא ישראל, Af al pi she'hu
Yisrael, although he's an Israelite, that תוספות Tosafot says phraseology goes on
the first half of that משנה, mishnah it does not really belong
here. Anyway, so what's the question? The question is is that if
you cannot get any fee for what you're doing and then and
then what exactly is the benefit one gets for having these ashes
of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah and this water of the פרה
אדומה? Parah Adumah?
Now it's a little funny question because you'll think the benefit of
the ashes, what? You have the same question, say it again?
I'm sorry. What? I'm
having the
same with the גמרא's Gemara question.
So it is hard to exactly, I'm trying, I'm explaining. It's hard
to understand exactly what the question is. It seems to be the
following, that there's two ways of framing the question and I have
to tell you I'm not I'm not fully at peace with either.
One way of framing the question is is that, oh, so if
you, meaning we might have thought let's say that the ashes of
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah were something that you couldn't get benefit
from and then it wouldn't be מקודשת. mekudeshet. But if you, but
if you can get benefit from it and it is, and it
is מקודשת, mekudeshet, then why can't you get paid? Now that's a
very strange question because the reason you can't get paid is not
because the object is אסור בהנאה, assur be'hana'ah, but is because you're
not supposed to get paid for doing a מצוה. mitzvah. It seems
rather, it seems rather the question is, I'm going to have to
ask a hold for the question now, we only have fifteen minutes.
It
seems rather the question is that, what's going on? Somebody, could somebody
put their microphone off?
Okay, okay.
It seems rather the question is
that,
I'm
sorry,
try it one more time, that, that, that, that you don't own
presumably the, the ashes of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, right? They're
owned by the ציבור. tzibur. So, so if you're giving them for
כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, it means that you can somehow make money
off of them. How could you make money off of them? Maybe
it's your job to go ahead and to mix them up or
whatever and by giving them to this woman to marry her, now,
you know, maybe she's going to be, she's going to do it
or maybe she'll give it to somebody else to do it or
maybe somehow having the ashes in your possession is some way can
allow you to make some money. So that maybe is how, that
is how I will frame the question, although I must admit that
I don't really understand the comparison too well. But if that's not,
you know, it does not seem to make too much sense the
comparison, but maybe that's the point, that if you're using it as
כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, it shows somehow you can make money off
of it. So let's take a look. So it says like this,
אמר אביי לא קשיא, Amar Abaye lo kashya, it's not
difficult, כאן בשכר הבאה ומילוי כאן בשכר הזאה וקידוש. Kan bischar hava'ah
u'milui kan bischar haza'ah ve'kiddush. One case you're getting paid for bringing
it, bringing the ashes from wherever from wherever they were burnt or
from filling up the buckets from the well. So that's not really
being paid for the מצוה mitzvah itself. That's being paid for all
of the preparation and the effort. That you are allowed to be
paid for and that would be the case where you're using it
for קידושין kiddushin and maybe then you're giving it to the woman
so she can make that money or she can sell it to
somebody else. There is money to be made in terms of the
effort that's
involved. But
כאן בשכר הזאה וקידוש, Kan bischar haza'ah ve'kiddush, to be paid for
the actual act of doing the sprinkling or the act of mixing
the ashes with the water, not with all of the effort that
preceded it, but the actual act of the מצוה, mitzvah, that you
are not allowed to be paid for. Okay, so, which by the
way is another way also about dealing with paying people's salaries. We're
not actually going to pay you for the time you're actually teaching
in class and doing the מצוה mitzvah תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, we're
going to pay you for all of the many, many hours you
spent ahead of time, you know, preparing and lesson plans and grading
and so on. So anyway, so we're basically saying that you can
get paid for the effort of the preparation but not for the
actual act of the מצוה mitzvah per se. דיקא נמי דקתני, Deika
nami de'katani, it's inferred from the language that it says,
הכא להזות ולקדש והתם, Hacha lehazot u'lekadesh ve'hatam, here it says that
you cannot get paid to sprinkle and to sanctify the ashes, which
is the actual act of the
מצוה. mitzvah. התם תני המקדש במי חטאת ובאפר חטאת, Hatam tani ha'mekadesh
be'mei chatat u've'efer chatat, there it says the water of the ashes,
that's because it was talking about an object, but maybe it means
the effort that's involved in the water and the ashes and not
the actual act of מצוה mitzvah per se. שמע מינה, shma mina,
that's a good proof. So again, the question is not so clear,
but the answer's important because it distinguishes from the מצוה mitzvah act
to the preparation, which you can be paid for. Now we move
on.
אם היה כהן מטמא מתרומתו, Im hayah Kohen mitamei mitrumaso, the כהן
Kohen became טמא, tamei then you can pay him for the additional
cost for food.
So it says the following: איהו גופיה היכי אזל? Ihu gufeh heichi
azil? So very nice, the כהן Kohen became טמא, tamei, but how
did he map who I mean why did he let himself go,
you know, go on a pathway, let's say in a graveyard, in
a cemetery and become טמא? tamei, He's transgressing the prohibition of becoming
טמא. tamei, So the גמרא Gemara says, לבית הפרס דרבנן, l'Beis HaPras
d'rabbanan, we're talking about a, remember the בית הפרס, Beis HaPras, a
field that has a lost grave somewhere where the problem is only
rabbinic.
דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מנפח אדם
בית הפרס והולך. minapeach adam Beis HaPras v'holech.
A person can blow through at in a בית הפרס Beis HaPras
and go, meaning you bend down, you blow a little bit in
front of you, which sifts out the dirt and sees that there's
no chip of bone and you take a step. You blow and
you take a step. So since you're allowed to do that, therefore
this works. Now what exactly that means, that's why there's a huge
תוספות. Tosafos. There're basically two ways to read it. Clearly you became
טמא tamei? as a result, or else we would not have the
case in the משנה mishna. that you have to pay the guy
for his additional food costs. So one thing the גמרא Gemara could
be saying is, the proof that it's only rabbinic is that you
can do this blowing and then you could be totally טהור. tahor.
So that shows that it's not so weighty, that shows it's only
rabbinic. And therefore even without doing this blowing, if you walked through,
it's true you're טמא, tamei. but it's not a biblical problem because
the whole thing is only rabbinic. So the blowing only demonstrates that
it's rabbinic, but in our scenario you actually just walked through straight,
became טמא, tamei. but you were allowed to do it, it was
only rabbinic, so you're allowed to do it for the מצוה. mitzvah.
Normally a כהן Kohen cannot walk through a בית הפרס Beis HaPras
because even if it's rabbinic, it's connected to the idea of טומאת
מת, tumas meis, but here for the sake of a מצוה mitzvah
we allow it. That's one way of reading the גמרא. Gemara The
other way of reading the גמרא gemara, is
that is
that yes, you did blow through, you did do the
blowing, and even when you do the blowing, you are actually still
going to remain טמא, tamei. which is interesting. The blowing will allow
you, make it permissible for you to do it, but we still
give you a טומאה tumah status.
So it's not exactly clear how the גמרא gemara is using the
blowing. Is it saying that that's what happened here, that you did
the blowing, but nevertheless even though we allow you under that scenario,
we're still going to say you're טמא? tamei? Or the fact that
the blowing works proves it's only rabbinic, and therefore in this case
you can do it without the blowing because it's a מצוה, mitzvah,
but again either way you remain טמא. tamei, So that's how we
explained why why the כהן Kohen was allowed to do it for
the sake of this מצוה, mitzvah, but he still was
טמא. tamei רב יהודה בר אמי משמיה דרב יהודה אמר בית הפרס
שנידוש טהור. Rav Yehuda bar Ami mishmei d'Rav Yehuda amar Beis HaPras
shenidosh tahor. No, it that if you, if you basically trample through
a בית הפרס, Beis HaPras, there's a path that people have been
going over, you know, so it became a whole trodden path, then
you can go on the trodden path because then we say that
if there were any chips of bone, they would have been totally
crushed and they won't make you טמא. Now of course the problem
is that's wonderful, but then why why are we saying that the
כהן Kohen became טמא? So again this seems to be saying not
that this is what happened here, because then he would be טהור,
tahor, but this proves that it's only a rabbinic concern and therefore
it's overridden for to allow the כהן kohen to do this מצוה
mitzvah of testifying, but nevertheless he is yes, he is טמא, but
it was only rabbinic and therefore he was allowed to do it
under these circumstances. That's one answer.
אי נמי, Ei nami, and of course the more simpler answer is
בשאר טומאות דלא מוזהר עלייהו. bish'ar tumos d'lo muzhar aleihu. Who says
we're talking about טומאת מת? tumas meis? Let's say the only way
to get from here to there was, you know, passing through a
place where you were going to touch a נבלה neveilah or touch
a שרץ, sharetz, you know, so that would be something that the
כהן is only prohibited against coming contact with the dead, but nevertheless
he came, became טמא a different way, which he was allowed to
do, but he still can't eat his תרומה. So that just explains
that case. Now אם היה זקן מרכיבו על החמור, Im hayah zaken
markivo al hachamor, if he you can put him on the donkey,
you can hire a car service, pay his expenses, and then the
key last line is you can pay for his time, שכרו. So
what does that mean? תנא כפועל בטל. Tana k'poel batel. You pay
for him like a like a worker who's doing nothing.
אמר אביי כפועל בטל של אותה מלאכה, Amar Abaye k'poel batel shel
osa melacha, who is taking off of that job. So what does
this mean? Very terse and ambiguous phrases. I would just say that
רש"י's Rashi explanation, which is the standard meaning, you say to somebody
how much would you take to to not work today and to
have a day off? So and then it depends. So first of
all, if I'm making a thousand dollars a day, I'm going to
ask for a lot more to take a day off than somebody
who's making ten dollars a day. Number one. Number two is if
my job is easy, and ironically as רש"י Rashi himself notes, he
gives the example of somebody who who cuts pearls. But we could
have said like, you know, a stock trader or something. You know,
somebody whose, sometimes some of the highest paying jobs are also the
jobs that involve, that are, can be more fun and have less,
you know, certainly involve less physical effort. So therefore, there is very
little incentive for me to take off my job. It's very high
paying and it's not too much work, so there's very little incentive.
So if you want me to take off my thousand dollar a
day job which has very little effort involved, you're going to have
to pay me nine hundred and fifty dollars. Whereas somebody who does
a lot of heavy work, number, you know, a, they're getting less
money, but b, also they're, they're much more prepared, they'd much rather
take a day off from like שלעפינג schlepping stones, you know, working
on a construction site. So then you might have to pay a
lot less for both reasons. You start with lesser amount and also
there's much more of an incentive for them to take off. So
it's really a very unfair system, but that's basically what happens in
terms of paying somebody for, for their lost opportunity time. Now, part
of the problem here is also, what about somebody who because they're
at the low end of the scale, they really can't afford to
take off? They might be making forty, fifty dollars a day, but
they won't even take, you know, maybe they'll take forty-nine dollars to
take off, but they might not even take that. They need every
single dollar. So even if it means a day off, they're not
going to take the money. You know, will that mean that their
שכר פועל בטל sechar poel batel is the full fifty dollars? Maybe
it will. I don't know. The other important question, which is why
we have another huge תוספות, Tosfos, is רש"י Rashi says, how much
would you take to take off of your job and to spend
the day being a judge or spend a day being a witness?
תוספות Tosfos says, whoa, you can't do that, because then you're actually
partially paying them for being a judge and being a witness. What
you have to do is say how much would you spend to
take the job, day off and be on the beach? Because, because,
you know, any time you say, if you include in it take
the day off and be a judge, then the amount goes up
because it's, I'm still exerting some effort for being a judge. And
therefore, you're partly paying me for being a judge. So that's an
interesting, this huge תוספות Tosfos is basically debating that point. Whether it's
how much you would
take to take a day on the beach or how much you
would take to take a day off and instead of your job
spend the day being a judge or being a witness. And תוספות
Tosfos very much emphasizes that it has to be a day on
the beach. Okay, so that is the question about how you determine
שכר בטלה, sechar batala, which is like lost opportunity cost. But again,
all of this becomes very, very important, like the רמב"ן, Ramban, we
were talking about teachers, the רמב"ן Ramban who was a doctor, everybody
knows רמב"ם Rambam was a doctor, not everyone knows רמב"ן Ramban was
a doctor. He has a whole question about how doctors can be
paid. They're also doing a מצוה mitzvah of saving lives. You know,
so, it raises a lot of very serious questions about how people
are paid and you don't just want to pay people for their
שכר בטלה, sechar batala, because that means again, you're paying people not
because they're better at what they're doing, but that they could be
better at doing something else. Which by the way, I think does
play out in, in the universities because law professors and business professors
are paid a lot more than professors of English literature, because law
professors and business professors could be making a lot more money out
in the real world. So anyway, sometimes it does play a role,
but still, you don't want your whole system based on that. So,
you know, there are again, one of the ways of answering it
is like the גמרא before about the effort that went beforehand. You're
not paying them for the actual job of the healing, you're paying
them first of all for all of the time that they spent
in medical school and all of the preparation and all of this,
but even that is a little bit of a fiction because you
still pay somebody for doing a surgery on you and you pay
differently for a surgery that took three hours and a surgery that
took, you know, thirty hours. So anyway, this raises a whole range
of questions and but this is the institution of שכר בטלה. sechar
batala. Okay, now, I heard this question
out, I would say, you know, was it understood that the, the
motivation to pay somebody for שכר בטלה, sechar batala, but they're quote-unquote,
like, you know, a real good person, are they, like, you know,
is there actually a value now, basically, yeah, you know, I understand
technically allowed to take this שכר בטלה, sechar batala, but in terms
of turning it down, now would we say that you can actually
take some of the שכר בטלה sechar batala
with no problem and then accept it as paying somebody, you know,
in any way? There's no, there's no point in turning down שכר
בטלה. sechar batala. There might be a point in turning down something
which is really a fee for services that is not שכר בטלה,
sechar batala, but the other point to be made if you're thinking
about the doctor is like a line that the גמרא in בבא
קמא Bava Kamma says, where the גמרא בבבא קמא Gemara B'Bava Kamma
says, you know, when it talks about somebody, you know, sending somebody
to a doctor who, who does it for free, the גמרא says,
a doctor who heals for nothing is worth nothing. So, you know,
and when you pay for things, obviously, you know, people, it changes
the whole, you know, it could very well determine the quality of
service you're getting and even if it's the same person, you know,
if you're paying them for their services, it could affect how the,
you know, the quality that they are providing. So it raises a
whole range of questions about how we work in our free market
economy together with the, you know, הלכה. halacha. the principles of not
being paid for doing מצוות. mitzvot. Let's at least get to the
next
משנה. mishna החשוד על הבכורות אין לוקחין ממנו בשר צבאים ולא עורות
שאינם עבודים. Hehashud al habechorot ein lokchin mimenu basar tzeva'im velo orot
she'einam avudim. If somebody is suspect for shechting animals that don't have
a blemish as a בכור, bechor, let's say he's a כהן or
whatever and somehow mysteriously whenever people give him their בכור bechor he
finds a blemish, you know, within a week and he's always shechting
them. So, we're not exactly sure that the animals he's shechting are
not בכור, bechor, are not unblemished בכור. bechor. So, in that type
of a case you cannot buy from him deer meat because deer
meat looks similar to lamb meat, he'll claim it's deer meat and
it's really lamb meat, they both I think also gamier, so therefore
they maybe taste similar, so maybe you're buying from him lamb meat
which is בכור bechor meat. ולא עורות שאינם עבודים velo orot she'einam
avudim and not untanned leather because maybe it's coming again from these
lambs. רבי אליעזר אומר לוקחין ממנו עור של נקבה, Rabbi Eliezer omer
lokchin mimenu or shel nekeva, you can buy them of females because
obviously they wouldn't have been a בכור bechor and when you get
the whole leather you see the genital area and you see whether
it's male or female.
ואין לוקחין ממנו צמר מלובן וצואי, ve'ein lokchin mimenu tzemer meluban vetzo'i,
you cannot buy from him cleansed like
white or dirty wool, meaning even the wool after it's been cleaned,
אבל לוקחין ממנו טווי ובגדים, aval lokchin mimenu tavi uvgadim, but you
can buy from him if it's already been sort of spun into
thread or garments. We'll see why in the גמרא, that could also
have come from the בכור. bechor. So, let's take a look. בשר
צבאים, basar tzeva'im, why can you not buy from him deer meat?
דמיחלף בדאגלא, demichlaf bed'agla, because it's confused with calf meat. Actually, I
said lamb meat here, it's calf meat. ולא עורות שאינם עבודים velo
orot she'einam avudim and not untanned leather. עבודים זבינא, avudim zabina, so
that means you can buy tanned leather. אם איתא דבכור הוה לא
הוה טרח בה, im ita debechor hava lo hava tarach bei, why
is that? Because
it's because if it really was the בכור bechor leather he would
not have gone to the effort to tan it, he would have
sold it as raw material. Why? סבר אי שמעו בי רבנן מפסידו
לי מינאי, savar ei sham'u bei rabanan mafsidu li minai, the rabbis
find out and are able to prove that I'm selling, you know,
בכור bechor stuff, they're going to take and seize the property or
declare it forbidden, which is essentially what our משנה has done. I'm
not going to put in all of the additional effort to tan
it if it might be that they come and they seize it
or whatever and they throw it out. So, therefore, I'll sell the
raw materials which is very little effort, but I'm not going to
put in much additional effort. רבי אליעזר אומר לוקחין ממנו עור של
נקבה, Rabbi Eliezer omer lokchin mimenu or shel nekeva, you can buy
those of a female.
מאי טעמא, what's the reason? מידי ידיע, midei yedia, because you can
look and see that it's a female. ותנא קמא, vetanna kamma, so
what does the תנא קמא tanna kamma think? אם כן זכר נמי
חתך לסיורתיה ואמר
עכברים אכלוהו, im ken zachar nami chatach lesiyuratei ve'amar achbarim achluhu, so
fine for a male skin what he'll do is he'll cut out
the genital area and he'll say that it was eaten by the
rats and he'll claim that it was a female skin.
ואידך, ve'idach, what would you say back? באכברים מידי ידיע, be'achbarim midei
yedia, you can see if the rats were eating have eaten from
it, it'll be obvious and he won't be able to make that
claim. So, if it does not if you can inspect it and
it has and it looks like a female skin you can take
it. ואין לוקחין ממנו צמר מלובן וצואי, ve'ein lokchin mimenu tzemer meluban
vetzo'i, you cannot take clean or white or white dirty wool. השתא
צמר מלובן לא זבנינן צואי מבעיא, hashta tzemer meluban lo zavninan tzo'i
mibaya, you can't take from him white wool even though he exerted
some effort to clean it, צואי מבעיא, tzo'i mibaya, is there any
question that you can't take dirty raw wool that he has not
exerted any effort? אלא חדא קתני צמר מלובן מצואתו, ela chada katani
tzemer meluban mitzo'ato, it's really saying one thing, צמר מלובן מצואתו. tzemer
meluban mitzo'ato. You could have just said it's like, you know, it's
fine, it's throwing you an extra, but it reads it as you
cannot take wool that has been cleansed from its dirt. Okay, and
the point being that even if he cleansed it that was not
a lot of effort, so it is still possible it's בכור, bechor,
but something that he exerted a lot of effort he would not
have done because he would be concerned that it would go to
waste. אבל לוקחין ממנו טווי ובגדים, aval lokchin mimenu tavi uvgadim, so
therefore you can buy from him spun wool and garments. השתא טווי
זבנינן בגדים מבעיא, hashta tavi zavninan bgadim mibaya, if you can buy
spun thread of course you can buy garments which is made out
of spun thread. So, no. מאי בגדים נמטי, mai bgadim namti, clothes
means like felt, pressed, so it's possible to have a type of
a pressed felt which is not spun, but even there because of
the effort involved we are not concerned that it is a בכור.
bechor. Now, what is the reason that you're not supposed to buy?
You could say you're not supposed to buy because you don't want
to derive הנאה hana'ah from things that are אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah.
That is the easiest reason to say why. But it's also worth
concerning considering the possibility that you also don't want to be indirectly
supporting this person's activities. And that gets into whole interesting questions like
the גמרא in בבא קמא Bava Kamma about buying stolen goods from
somebody. That on the one hand, you know, am I doing an
איסור issur myself by doing this? But forget with, if you're providing
a market then you are basically, you know, you are basically encouraging
and allowing and supporting that activity and that also becomes a problem.
So, it's worth thinking about both reasons, but the more obvious reason
is because it would be אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah if it really
was a בכור תם. bechor tam. Let's go together and read just
the next little line and I know we're a little over, but
just two more lines. החשוד Hehashud החשוד על השביעית אין לוקחין ממנו
פשתן. Hachashud Al Hashevi'it Ein Lokchin Mimenu Pishtan.
If somebody is suspect for
either for שמיטה, Shmita, either for raising the stuff without making it
הפקר Hefker or for doing business in שמיטה, Shmita, then you cannot
buy from that person flax, we're concerned it's שמיטה, Shmita, ואפילו סרוק,
Ve'afilu Saruk, even if it's combed flax, אבל לוקחין ממנו טווי ואריג,
Aval Lokchin Mimenu Tavi Ve'arig, similarly you can buy it once it's
spun and made into a garment, because at that stage he would
not put in that amount of effort, he'd be afraid that it
would go to waste, the rabbis would find out and take it.
השתא טווי זבנינן אריג מיבעיא, Hashta Tavi Zavninan Arig Mibaya, if you
can buy spun, of course you can buy woven, so מאי אריג?
Mai Arig? טיכי. Tichi. No, when it says woven, it means like
unspun wool made into chains. So again, there's different types of ways,
but the point being that anything that required a certain degree of
effort, we are not concerned that that is forbidden because then he
would not want to risk losing all of the effort that he
put in. So we will continue with all of this tomorrow in
person. Take care everybody. Bye.